Guide to the Gibbs-Van Name Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Gibbs-Van Name papers
1843-1959
1929-1957
GEN MSS 83
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.5
(8 boxes)
The papers contain correspondence and other materials documenting the efforts of Ralph gibbs Van Name to publish technical and biographical work on Josiah Willard Gibbs, the scientist who developed the theory of thermodynamics.
Van Name, Ralph Gibbs, 1877-1961
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Many of the papers were originally part of the Gibbs Family Papers in Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, which were transferred to the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library in December 1982. Additional Gibbs-Van Name papers were donated to Beinecke Library by Theodora Van Name Palmer in 1961.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 8: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
JOSIAH WILLARD GIBBS (1839-1903)
Josiah Willard Gibbs, mathematician and physicist, was born in New Haven on February 11, 1839, the son of Josiah Willard Gibbs, professor of sacred literature at Yale, and Mary Anna Van Cleve. He received a B.A. from Yale in 1858, an M.A. in 1861, and a Ph.D. in 1863. After serving as tutor in Latin (1863-65) and natural philosophy (1865-66), Gibbs went to Europe to study for three years. He returned to New Haven in 1869 and was appointed professor of mathematical physics at Yale in 1871, a position he held until his death.
Best known for developing the theory of thermodynamics, Gibbs wrote a number of extremely important and influential scientific works, the most significant being "Graphical Methods in the Thermodynamics of Fluids" (1873), "A Method of Geometrical Representation of the Thermodynamic Properties of Substances by Means of Surfaces" (1873), "On the Equilibrium of Heterogeneous Substances" (1876, 1878), "Electrochemical Thermodynamics" (1886, 1888), and Elementary Principles in Statistical Mechanics (1902).
He lived at the home of his sister and brother-in-law, Julia Gibbs and Addison Van Name, and died unmarried in New Haven on April 28, 1903.
For additional biographical information, see the Dictionary of American Biography, IV, pp. 248-51; Muriel Rukeyser, Willard Gibbs (1942), and Lynde Phelps Wheeler, Josiah Willard Gibbs, the History of a Great Mind (1951).
RALPH GIBBS VAN NAME (1877-1961)
Ralph Gibbs Van Name was born in New Haven on October 22, 1877. The son of Addison and Julia Gibbs Van Name and nephew of Josiah Willard Gibbs, he was educated at Yale, receiving a B.A. in 1899 and a Ph.D. in 1902. Van Name was an instructor at Yale 1904-09, assistant professor 1909-24, associate professor of physical chemistry 1924-36, research associate in chemistry 1936-44, and research associate emeritus until his death on January 4, 1961. On June 25, 1925 he married Josephine Earl; the couple had two children, John Addison and Virginia Gibbs Van Name.
While serving on the Yale faculty, Van Name devoted much attention to memorializing the life and work of his uncle Josiah Willard Gibbs. He helped edit The Scientific Papers of J. Willard Gibbs (1906) and through the Gibbs Memorial Fund assisted in the publication of The Collected Works of J. Willard Gibbs (1928) and A Commentary on the Scientific Writings of J. Willard Gibbs (1936). He also provided assistance to biographers Muriel Rukeyser and Lynde Phelps Wheeler.
Scope and Contents
The Gibbs-Van Name Papers consist primarily of Ralph Gibbs Van Name's correspondence; they document the publishing of technical and biographical works on his uncle Josiah Willard Gibbs (1839-1903). The papers are divided into five series, each alphabetically and chronologically arranged by material type. They span the dates 1843-1959, with the bulk of the material covering the years 1929-57.
Series I, Collected Works, contains correspondence and papers concerning the establishment of the Gibbs Memorial Fund and the republishing in 1928 of The Collected Works of J. Willard Gibbs. Included in the series are letters from Edwin B. Wilson and G. A. Hewlett, an agreement to establish a memorial fund, committee reports and notes, and a typescript of the introduction which summarizes the committee's work. Printed works include reviews.
Series II, Commentary, documents the writing, editing, and publishing of the two-volume work, A Commentary on the Scientific Writings of Josiah Willard Gibbs (1936). F. G. Donnan of University College, London, edited volume I and Arthur Haas of the University of Vienna edited volume II. As supervising administrator for the project, Ralph Gibbs Van Name maintained a steady flow of correspondence with the editors. His correspondence with Yale treasurer George Parmly Day and president James Rowland Angell concerns the financial difficulties of publishing the volumes during the depression. Other prominent correspondents include Irving Fisher, Paul Epstein, George W. Morey, and William F. G. Swann. Memorandum and payments to authors complement the correspondence.
The papers concerned with the first of two modern biographies of Josiah Willard Gibbs are found in Series III. In her Willard Gibbs: American Genius (1942), Muriel Rukeyser (1913-1980) intended to discuss Gibbs's life, personality, and scientific importance, but the Van Name family was not pleased with her research or with the completed biography. The correspondence provides insights on Ralph Gibbs Van Name's character, Van Name family relationships, and the sentiments of Gibbs's former students. Correspondents include Theodora Van Name, Norman Holmes Pearson, William Lyon Phelps, and Edwin B. Wilson. Much of Ralph Gibbs Van Name's correspondence addresses his misgivings about Rukeyser's abilities as a biographer, which resulted in his decision to withhold family correspondence from her. Van Name called upon former students to review the biography in the hope of discrediting it. Folders 122-26 contain reviews of the book. Rukeyser generally received favorable literary reviews and mixed scientific ones. Miscellaneous genealogical notes are also found, probably written by Theodora Van Name to help answer questions raised by Rukeyser.
Series IV, Lynde Phelps Wheeler, contains correspondence and other papers relating to Wheeler's biography, Josiah Willard Gibbs: The Historyof a Great Mind (1951). After publication of Rukeyser's biography, Van Name asked Wheeler to help compile reminiscences of Gibbs for future biographical research. Later he encouraged Wheeler to write a Gibbs biography to counteract the image Rukeyser created. The series contains correspondence with several associates of Gibbs, including Irving Fisher, Edwin B. Wilson, and George W. Morey. The series also includes a complete list of Gibbs's living students in 1944 and a number of reviews of Wheeler's book.
The final series, Additional Papers, includes a variety of information on Gibbs, Ralph Gibbs Van Name, the Van Name family, and the Gibbs family. Biographical inquiries contain requests for information on Gibbs and Van Name's responses. Biographical works include sketches of Gibbs that shed light on attitudes towards him as a professor, scientist, and an individual. The estate and family papers provide genealogical charts, copies of early Gibbs correspondence, and financial records. Gibbs Memorial and Hall of Fame material combine to describe how the memorial was established and its financial connection with the Hall of Fame nomination. Also included are lecture notes taken by Van Name in 1899-1900 for a class taught by Gibbs, photographs, press releases on the USNS Josiah Willard Gibbs, and printed material.
The papers present a relatively complete account of efforts by Van Name to publish Gibbs's works, to encourage biographical studies of him, and to enhance his reputation. Through the correspondence and biographical sketches the character of J. Willard Gibbs and the Van Name family are revealed.
Authors, American; Biography; Publishers and publishing; Biographers -- United States; Scientists -- United States; Angell, James Rowland, 1869-1949; Day, George Parmly, 1876-1959; Donnan, F. G. (Frederick George), 1870-1956; Epstein, P. (Paul), 1871-; Fisher, Irving, 1867-1947; Gibbs, J. Willard (Josiah Willard), 1839-1903; Haas, Arthur Erich, 1884-1941; Hewlett, G. A.; Johnston, John, 1881-1950; Morey, G. W. (George Washington), 1888-1965; Pearson, Norman Holmes, 1909-1975; Rukeyser, Muriel, 1913-1980; Swann, W. F. G. (William Francis Gray), 1884-1962; Van Name, Ralph Gibbs, 1877-1961; Van Name, Theodora; Van Name, Willard G. (Willard Gibbs), 1872-1959; Wheeler, Lynde Phelps, 1874-1959; Gibbs family; Van Namee family; Yale University Press; Yale University -- Faculty
- Collected Works, 1927-1948; Series I; 0.25; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Collected Works consists of alphabetically arranged correspondence, followed by related papers.
  - Correspondence
    - "A-B" general, 1927-44 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "C" general, 1927-33, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "D" general, 1927-37 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "E-F" general, 1927-30 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "G-J" general, 1924-30 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "K-L" general, 1930-48 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Longmans, Green & Company, 1927-31 (Box 1, Folder 7-11)
    - "M-W" general, 1930-48 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Agreement, 1948 Jun (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Committee report and notes, 1927 May (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Introduction: typescript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Printed material, 1906-48, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Reviews, 1929, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous papers, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Commentary, 1908-1946; Series II; 0.75; (2 boxes)
  Series II, Commentary, contains alphabetically arranged correspondence, followed by related papers.
  - Correspondence
    - Andrews, Donald H., 1931-35, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Angell, James Rowland, 1932-36 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - "B" general, 1928-33 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - "C" general, 1928-46 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - "D" general, 1928-33 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Day, George Parmly, 1926-36, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 24-28)
    - Donnan, F. G., 1928-1938,n.d. (Box 2, Folder 29-41)
    - "E-J" general, 1928-36, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Epstein, Paul, 1929-36, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 43-44)
    - Fisher, Irving, 1928-36, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 45-46)
    - Haas, Arthur, 1928-35 (Box 2, Folder 47-56)
    - Haas, Arthur, 1936, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 57-58)
    - "J" general, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Johnston, John, 1928-36, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - "K" general, 1927-36 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - "L" general, 1927-36 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - "M" general, 1928-36 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - McGraw-Hill Book Company, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Morey, George W., 1927-37, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 65-67)
    - "N-R" general, 1927-37 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - "S" general, 1927-28 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Swann, William, F. G., 1927-36 (Box 3, Folder 70-71)
    - "T" general, 1927-28, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - "W-Z" general, 1927-28 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - Wilson, Edwin B., 1927-36 (Box 3, Folder 74-77)
    - Yale University Press, 1933-36 (Box 3, Folder 78-80)
    - Letter fragments, 1927-36, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Memorandum: Committee on "Protokoll", 1929, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1927-37, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 83-84)
  - Payments to authors, 1929-36, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 85-90)
  - Printed material
    - Nature, 1928 Feb (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - Science, 1928 Apr (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - Miscellaneous, 1908-37, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 93)
- Muriel Rukeyser, 1906-1952; Series III; 0.5; (1 box)
  Series III, Muriel Rukeyser, is composed of alphabetically arranged correspondence, followed by
  - Correspondence
    - "C" general, 1942-43 (Box 4, Folder 94)
    - Doubleday, Doran and Company, 1941-42 (Box 4, Folder 95)
    - "E-F" general, 1944-45 (Box 4, Folder 96)
    - Fisher, Irving, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 97)
    - Gesell, Arnold, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 98)
    - "H-L" general, 1942-44 (Box 4, Folder 99)
    - Johnston, John, 1942-43 (Box 4, Folder 100)
    - "M" general, 1942-43 (Box 4, Folder 101)
    - Pearson, Norman Holmes, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 102)
    - Phelps, William Lyon, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 103)
    - Rukeyser, Muriel, 1940-42 (Box 4, Folder 104-105)
    - Van Name, Theodora, 1940-44, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 106-107)
    - Wilson, Edwin B., 1940-49 (Box 4, Folder 108-115)
    - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 116)
  - Articles, 1941-52 (Box 4, Folder 117)
  - Biographical information, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 118)
  - Excerpts from biography: typescript, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 119)
  - Notebooks: Theodora Van Name, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 120)
  - Printed material: The Scientific Papers of J. Willard Gibbs, 1906 (Box 4, Folder 121)
  - Reviews, 1943, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 122-25)
  - Scrapbook, 1941-43 (Box 4, Folder 126)
  - Miscellaneous papers
    - Envelopes, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 127)
    - Genealogical notes, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 128-29)
- Lynde Phelps Wheeler, 1906-1957; Series IV; 0.5; (1 box)
  Series IV contains alphabetically arranged correspondence and additional related papers. An
  - Correspondence
    - "D-F" general, 1947-49 (Box 5, Folder 130)
    - Fisher, Irving, 1944-57 (Box 5, Folder 131-34)
    - Gale, Arthur S., 1945-47 (Box 5, Folder 135)
    - Herrick, Samuel, 1949-53 (Box 5, Folder 136)
    - Morey, George W., 1956 (Box 5, Folder 137)
    - "O-P" general, 1931-52 (Box 5, Folder 138)
    - "S-W" general, 1947-52 (Box 5, Folder 139)
    - Simon and Schuster, Inc. Publishers, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 140)
    - Wheeler, Lynde Phelps, 1944-57, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 141-54)
    - Willard, F. W., 1944 (Box 5, Folder 155)
    - Wilson, Edwin B., 1944-57 (Box 5, Folder 156)
  - Notes, 1944, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 157-60)
  - Printed material: miscellaneous, 1906-51 (Box 5, Folder 161)
  - Reviews, 1951, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 162-64)
  - Writings: "The Early Works of Willard Gibbs in Applied Mechanics," by Samuel Dudley, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 165)
  - Miscellaneous envelopes, 1951, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 166)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1946-52, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 167)
- Additional Papers, 1843-1959; Series V; 1; (3 boxes)
  The papers in Series V are alphabetically arranged by person and subject.
  - Article: unidentified, 1933-38, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 168-76)
  - Biographical inquiries: correspondence, 1905-53 (Box 6, Folder 177-83)
  - Biographical works
    - Donan, F. G.: typescript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 184)
    - Fisher, Irving: typescript, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 185)
    - Johnston, John: correspondence, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 186)
    - Johnston, John: galley, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 187)
    - Johnston, John: manuscript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 188)
    - Johnston, John: typescript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 189-90)
  - Estate papers, 1903-07 (Box 6, Folder 191-98)
  - Family papers
    - Correspondence: manuscript and typed copies, 1843-88 (Box 6, Folder 199)
    - Dasburg, Alfred: correspondence, 1951-52 (Box 6, Folder 200-01)
    - Donations to Yale University, 1920-51, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 202)
    - Genealogical notes, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 203)
    - Photographs, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 204)
    - Van Name, Addison, 1906, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 205)
  - Gibbs, Josiah Willard
    - Dissertation, "On the Form of the Teeth of Wheels in Spur Gearing": Correspondence, 1937-45 (Box 7, Folder 206-07)
    - Paper, "The Proper Magnitude of Units of Length": typescript, 1866 Mar 21 (Box 7, Folder 208)
  - Gibbs Memorial
    - Committee report, 1927 May (Box 7, Folder 209)
    - Correspondence, 1910-28, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 210-11)
    - Description, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 212)
    - Minutes, 1927-28, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 213)
    - Proposal, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 214)
    - Resolution, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 215)
  - Hall of Fame
    - Correspondence, 1940-57 (Box 7, Folder 216)
    - Memorandum (Box 7, Folder 217)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 218)
  - Lecture: Whitney, Margaret D., 1937 (Box 7, Folder 219)
  - Lecture: correspondence and text, 1938-39, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 220)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1906-51, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 221-24)
  - Printed material, 1881-1945 (Box 7, Folder 225-32)
  - Sheffield Scientific School, 1947-49 (Box 7, Folder 233-34)
  - USNS Josiah Willard Gibbs, 1958-59, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 235-39)
  - Van Name, Ralph Gibbs
    - Lecture notes: class from Josiah Willard Gibbs, 1899-1900 (Box 7, Folder 240)
    - Notes, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 241)
    - Notes, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 242-46)
    - Miscellaneous papers, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 247-52)
- Restricted Fragile Papers, Series VI
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 8: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 2, folder 43 (Box 8, Folder 253)
  - Box 3, folder 57 (Box 8, Folder 254)
  - Box 5, folders 139, 155 (Box 8, Folder 255)